Guide to the Full Frame Archive Collection, 1998-2017 RL.00424
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Full Frame Archive collection
1998-2017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.00424
55.5 Linear Feet
The Full Frame Documentary Film Festival is the largest film festival in the United States entirely devoted to documentary film. Originally the DoubleTake Documentary Film Festival, it is an international event dedicated to the theatrical exhibition of non-fiction cinema, held annually since 1998 in downtown Durham, North Carolina. Typically, more than 100 films are screened, along with discussions, panels, and workshops fostering conversation between filmmakers, film professionals and the public. The Full Frame Archive was created in 2007, as a partnership between Duke University and Full Frame. The Full Frame Archive Film Collection comprises preservation masters of documentary films that won awards at the Full Frame Film Festival between 1998 and 2012. Formats include 35mm film, 16mm film, Digital Betacam cassette, HDCAM cassette, Betacam SP cassette, and DVD. In addition, there is a complete set of festival program books. The films vary widely in topic and style, with a predominant emphasis on human rights issues; all of the films deal with social issues in one way or another. The collection is organized chronologically, by festival year, and acquisitions are ongoing.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Full Frame Archive Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift between 2007 and 2017. Acquisitions are ongoing.
Historical Note
The Full Frame Documentary Film Festival is the largest film festival in the United States entirely devoted to documentary film. An international event dedicated to the theatrical exhibition of non-fiction cinema, the Festival is held annually for four days in the spring in downtown Durham, North Carolina. Typically, more than 100 films are screened, along with discussions, panels, and workshops fostering conversation between filmmakers, film professionals and the public.
Full Frame's mission, as stated in 2010, is to support the documentary form and community by showcasing the contemporary work of established and emerging filmmakers and by preserving film heritage through archival efforts and continued exhibition of classic documentaries. The organization is also committed to building wider national and international audiences for documentary film and enhancing public understanding and appreciation of the art form and its significance.
Originally named the DoubleTake Documentary Film Festival, it was launched in 1998 under the leadership of Nancy Buirski, in association with the Center for Documentary Studies (CDS) at Duke University and DoubleTake Magazine, an acclaimed journal published by CDS from 1995-1998. Buirski expressed the Festival's mission that year as "to see documentary films take their rightful place in the pantheon of film festivals and in the hearts of film lovers" (Festival Program 1998). She described its uniqueness as lying "in its focus on film content, its emphasis on issues that matter, and its ability to reach out to the community and act as a bridge to its concerns" (ibid.)
DoubleTake Magazine ceased to be associated with the festival after 1999, and from 2000 on, the Festival was presented by Documentary Arts, Inc. (a 501(c)(3) non-profit organization founded by Nancy Buirski and later renamed Doc Arts, Inc.), in association with the CDS. The festival was renamed "Full Frame Documentary Film Festival" for the 2002 festival. Duke University withdrew as a presenting sponsor from 2003 through 2005. The New York Times joined as a presenting sponsor from 2003 through 2008 festival. From 2006 to 2010, Duke University returned as presenting sponsor. In the fall of 2010, Full Frame became once again a program of the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University. The festival also receives support from a large number of corporate sponsors, private foundations and individual donors.
Each year, a series or thematic program is foregrounded, curated by established filmmakers. In addition, there has usually been one or two "sidebar" series presented, one of which focuses on the American South. The bulk of the programming, however, has always been devoted to new documentaries in competition; a selection committee consisting of local volunteer professionals chooses a few dozen films for screening, considering original content and technical proficiency primarily, from a pool of 100 to 1000 submissions from filmmakers from around the world. Several awards are then given at the conclusion of the Festival; the Grand Jury and Audience Awards have been awarded every year, and additional awards have been added from year to year. These award-winning films comprise the Full Frame Archive's collection.
In 2007, Duke University Libraries and Full Frame announced the creation of the Full Frame Archive, to be housed in Duke's David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, to acquire, archive and preserve copies of all of the Festival's award-winning films, with support from Eastman Kodak and Alpha Cine Labs, Seattle.
Chronology List
1998 April 2-5 The first DoubleTake Documentary Film Festival was held at The Carolina Theatre in downtown Durham, the North Carolina Museum of Art and the Omni Hotel. There were twenty-eight films screened in competition, selected from a pool of 107 submissions; films by Richard Kotuk, Jan Krawitz, Jonathan Stack, and Liz Garbus won the first set of DoubleTake Awards.
1999 April 8-11 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre and the Civic Center. Twenty-eight films were screened in competition, selected from over 300 submissions; films by Dariusz Jablonski, Frieda Lee Mock, Terry Sanders, and Elisabeth Leuvrey took the top honors.
2000 April 6-9 Festival was held at the Caroline Theatre and the Civic Center. There were 425 films submitted for competition. Jean-Stephane Bron, Edward Rosenstein, Linda Duvoisin, and Eugene Richards earned awards for their films.
2001 May 3-6 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, the Durham Arts Council and the Marriott Hotel. "A record number of submissions for competition were received, 530, from which 57 were selected for screening; award-winning filmmakers included Marie de Laubier, Jem Cohen, Peter Sillen, Stephen Ives, and Rohan Sen.
2002 April 4-7 The renamed Full Frame Documentary Film Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, the Durham Arts Council and the Marriott Hotel. Sixty-seven films were presented in competition, selected from 600 submissions. Films by Davis Guggenheim, Steven Silver, and Nilesh Patel were among the award winners.
2003 April 10-13 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, the Durham Arts Council and the Armory. Award-winning filmmakers this year included Nicolas Philibert, Jesse Moss, and Emily James.
2004 April 1-4 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Arts Council's PSI Theatre, the Armory, with special events held at various offsite venues. Sixty-six films were chosen for competition, from over 700 submissions. Award winners included Jehane Noujaim, Ross Kaufman, Zana Briski, and Melba Williams.
2005 April 7-10 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, the Armory, the American Tobacco Campus, and Durham Arts Council. From more than 930 submissions, 77 films were selected for competition, and films by Henry Alex Rubin, Dana Adam Shapiro, Leonard Retel Helmrich, Alessandro Cassigoli, and Dalia Castel were among a growing roster of award winners.
2006 April 6-9 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Arts Council, the Civic Center Theatre and American Tobacco Campus. Seventy-two films were selected from 1100 submissions for competition; award winners included James Longley, Ricki Stern, Annie Sundberg, and Laura Paglin. Over 20,000 tickets were sold. The Full Frame Institute was created to emphasize year-round curated programs and mentorships.
2007 April 12-15 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Civic Center, American Tobacco Campus and Durham Arts Council, plus assorted Non-Theatrical Venues sponsored by the City of Durham. In commemoration of the Festival's tenth year, aA special thematic program "The Power of Ten," presented ten films selected by "ten of the artists who make up the Full Frame family" (Buirski, introduction to the thematic program) in commemoration of the tenth year of the Full Frame Documentary Film Festival. From over 1100 submissions, 82 were selected for competition; films by Pernille Rose Grønkjær, Sean Fine, Andrea Nix Fine, and Ben Wu were among the award winners. Nancy Buirski resigned/retired as Full Frame CEO and Artistic Director after this festival.
2008 April 3-6 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Civic Center, Durham School of the Arts, and Durham Arts Council, as well as various non-theatrical venues sponsored by the City of Durham Dept. of Parks and Recreation. Award winners included films by Carl Deal, Tia Lessin, Jams Marsh, and Eva Weber. The Full Frame Archive was announced.
2009 April 2-5 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Convention Center and Durham Arts Council as well as various non-theatrical venues. Fifty-nine films were screened for competition; winners included films by Anders Østergaard, Aron Gaudet, and Andreas Koefoed.
2010 April 8-11 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Convention Center, Durham Arts Council, and Durham Central Park (free outdoor screenings were offered for the first time). This was the first festival under the leadership of executive director Dierdre Haj. From 1,200 submissions, 57 new films were selected for competition. Award-winning films included those by Rob Lemkin, Thet Sambath, Lucy Walker and Elham Asadi.
2011 April 14-17 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Convention Center, Durham Arts Council, and Durham Central Park. From over 1,200 submissions, 66 new films were selected for competition. Award-winning films included those by Cindy Meehl, Grover Babcock, Blue Hadaegh, and Rodrigo Dorfman. This was the first year that Full Frame was once again under the auspices of the Center for Documentary Studies and Duke University.
2012 April 12-15 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Convention Center, Durham Arts Council, and Durham Central Park. From over 1,200 submissions, 57 new films were selected for competition. Award-winning films included those by Andrew Garrison, Fernand Melgar, and Mira Jargil.
2013 April 4-7 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Convention Center, Durham Arts Council, and Durham Central Park.
2014 April 3-6 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Convention Center, Durham Arts Council, and Durham Central Park.
2015 April 9-12 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Convention Center, Durham Arts Council, and Durham Central Park.
2016 April 7-10 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Convention Center, Durham Arts Council, and Durham Central Park.
2017 April 6-9 Festival was held at the Carolina Theatre, Durham Convention Center, Durham Arts Council, and Durham Central Park.
Collection Overview
The Full Frame Archive comprises program material, publicity-related material, and preservation masters of award-winning documentary films at the Full Frame Documentary Film Festival (formerly DoubleTake) between 1998 and 2017. Film formats include 35mm film, 16mm film, Digital Betacam cassette, HDCAM cassette, Betacam SP cassette, and DVD. In addition, the collection contains festival program books, postcards, movie posters, t-shirts, tote bags, advertisements, newspaper clippings, press releases, and newspaper inserts.
The collection is organized chronologically, by festival year. Each series in the collection includes all acquired award winners from one year and available program material, when available. Each subseries comprises all the elements for one documentary work.
Whenever possible, the film is preserved on 35mm film, a duplicate preservation master especially created for this collection; occasionally, the work was originally filmed on 35mm, but more often it was recorded digitally and then transferred to film for festival screenings and theatrical release. Many films were never transferred to film, and in those cases, the highest quality digital master has been preserved, usually on Digital Betacam cassette, cloned from the master provided by the filmmaker or production company; other digital formats are represented as well.
While all are documentary films, some may also be considered belonging to the genres of biographical nonfiction, ethnographic, ethnic nonfiction and music. Feature, short and animation forms are all represented. The films vary widely in topic and style, with a predominant emphasis on human rights issues. All of the films deal with social issues in one way or another, including topics such as gender; family relations; education; life cycles (childhood, aging, death, etc.); crime and justice; minority groups and discrimination; public health; humanitarian aid; technology and social life; migration; democracy; economic development; war and conflict; peace and healing; art and society; religion; rehabilitation; etc.
Competition for awards has always been international; though the majority of award-winners are from and about the United States, the collection is also notably strong on topics relating to Africa and the Middle East. Only films completed within one year of the festival were eligible for competition, thus all are contemporary to the festival date. The number and type of awards given at the Festival changed from year to year; thus, each year is represented by a different number of films, selected according to varying criteria.
The Full Frame Archive was begun in late 2007 and acquisitions are ongoing. The films are donated by the filmmaker and/or copyright holder. Although the intent is to eventually preserve every Full Frame award winner, this may not be possible, as some copyright holders may decline to donate their work.
These preservation masters are stored in a climate-controlled facility off-site and may not be viewed. For viewing purposes, DVD use copies are available, backed up by a DVD master, also stored off-site.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged by year of festival, then by film and material.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Use copies are available in the collection.
Documentary films -- Awards; Documentary films -- Middle East; Education in motion pictures; Economic development; Documentary films -- Social aspects; Documentary films -- Production and direction; Documentary films -- Africa; Documentary films -- United States; Film festivals -- North Carolina; Families; Criminology; Criminal justice, Administration of; Art and society; Programs (documents); Film festivals -- Awards; Film festivals -- Programs; Discrimination; Democracy; 35mm; 16mm; Documentary films -- History and criticism; Documentary films -- Political aspects; DVDs; Digital Betacam (TM); Betacam-SP; Peace -- Social aspects; Peace; Public health; Religion; Technology -- Social aspects; War; Refugees; Rehabilitation; Film festivals -- United States; Film festivals; Gender; Human rights in motion pictures; Humanitarian assistance; Life cycle, Human; Minorities; Motion picture producers and directors; Documentaries (motion picture genre); Celebrations -- Durham (N.C.); Full Frame Documentary Film Festival; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies. DoubleTake
- DoubleTake Film Festival, 1998
  - The Farm: Angola USA (1998)
    Scope and Contents note
    Directed by: Jonathan Stack and Liz Garbus
    Produced by: Gabriel Films
    Country: United States
    Award won: DoubleTake Grand Audience Award
    TRT: 91:00
    A documentary about the Louisiana State Penitentiary at Angola, nicknamed "The Farm," this film follows six inmates in a controlled and non-judgmental fashion, subtly revealing the inner-workings of an American way of life not often investigated. The culmination of three years spent filming inside the penitentiary walls, The Farm speaks of the hopes and struggles of those who may never experience freedom again.
    Existence and Location of Copies note
    Use Copies: DVD use copy available.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 91:00 (Box 5)
    - DVD master, TRT 91:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - In Harm's Way (1998)
    Directed by: Jan Krawitz
    Produced by: Jan Krawitz
    Award won: DoubleTake Grand Jury Award
    TRT: 27:00
    This is an intensely personal documentary that explores the concept of safety within the context of a society that sometimes gives rise to random acts of violence. Krawitz offers viewers an affecting portrait of her own life story, told through contemporary images and excerpts from the "safety first" films shown in school classrooms during the 1950s and '60s.
    - Preservation print, 16mm, so., col., reel 1 of 1, 972 ft. (Box 1)
    - DVD master, TRT 27:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Travis (1998)
    Directed by: Richard Kotuk
    Produced by: Richard Kotuk
    TRT: 56:40
    An unsentimental portrait of a seven-year-old African American boy who has AIDS, this film witnesses Travis's struggle, with the support of his grandmother and family, for the opportunity to be a boy with normal childhood dreams, as he faces death and yearns for life.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 56:40 (Box 3)
    - DVD master, TRT 56:40 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Festival materials, 1998
    - Newspaper Insert, 1998 (Box 19)
    - Program Book, 1998 DoubleTake Film Festival (1998) (Box 6)
    - Programs and News Clippings, 1998 (Box 13)
    - T-Shirt, 1998 (Box 13)
    - Tote Bag, 1998 (Box 13)
- DoubleTake Film Festival, 1999
  - Fotoamator (1999)
    English title: The Photographer
    Director: Dariusz Jablonski
    Producer: Dariusz Jablonski
    Country: Poland
    Awards won: DoubleTake Grand Jury Award
    TRT: 80:00
    This film documents life in the Lodz Ghetto during the Nazi occupation of Poland, using a remarkable, recently discovered collection of color slides made by Walter Genewein, the Ghetto's chief Nazi accountant, who observed the people of the Ghetto with a cold, calculating eye. Genewein's pictures are juxtaposed with sorrowful and eloquently narrated memories of Arnold Mostowics, a Jewish medical doctor who survived the Lodz Ghetto and concentration camps. The film's riveting power comes from the tension between the two perspectives.
    In German and Polish with English subtitles.
    - 35mm print, So., co., reel 1 of 4, 1710 ft. (Reel 73)
    - 35mm print, So., co., reel 2 of 4, 1710 ft. (Reel 74)
    - 35mm print, So., co., reel 3 of 4, 1710 ft. (Reel 75)
    - 35mm print, So., co., reel 4 of 4, 1710 ft. (Reel 76)
    - DVD master, TRT 80:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Return With Honor (1998)
    Directors: Freida Lee Mock and Terry Sanders
    Producer: American Film Foundation
    TRT: 102:00
    During the Vietnam War era, the American people were split over their country's involvement overseas. But in 1973, thousands united to welcome home 462 American pilots held captive in North Vietnam for up to eight years. The first-person survival accounts of the pilots and the testimonies of their wives, who for so long did not know the status of their husbands, are woven together with Vietnamese archival footage to record a moving story of mental, physical and emotional resiliency.
    - 35mm print, So., co., reel 1 of 6, 1530 ft. (Reel 50)
    - 35mm print, So., co., reel 2 of 6, 1530 ft. (Reel 51)
    - 35mm print, So., co., reel 3 of 6, 1530 ft. (Reel 52)
    - 35mm print, So., co., reel 4 of 6, 1530 ft. (Reel 53)
    - 35mm print, So., co., reel 5 of 6, 1530 ft. (Reel 54)
    - 35mm print, So., co., reel 6 of 6, 1530 ft. (Reel 55)
    - DVD master, TRT 102:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Festival materials, 1999
    - Program Book, 1999 DoubleTake Film Festival (1999) (Box 6)
    - Programs and News Clippings, 1999 (Box 13)
    - T-Shirt, 1999 (Box 13)
    - Tote Bag, 1999 (Box 13)
    - Newspaper Insert, 1999 (Box 19)
- DoubleTake Film Festival, 2000
  - The Gospel According to Mr. Allen (2000)
    Directed by: Edward Rosenstein
    Produced by: Edward Rosenstein and Jonathan Stack
    Award won: DoubleTake Audience Award
    TRT: 52:00
    When James Allen opened the Addicts Rehabilitation Center in Harlem it was New York State's first residential treatment center for people without money. Forty-three years later, on some of America's meanest streets, the doors are still open. This film follows three addicts through A.R.C. as they try to break the grip of drugs. Can the battle against poverty, hopelessness and addiction ever be won? Famed for its tough-love, trash-talking staff and its gospel choir, the Addicts Rehabilitation Center never gives up on people.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 52:00 (Box 3)
    - DVD master, TRT 52:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - You Don't Know What I Got (2000)
    Directed by: Linda Duvoisin
    Produced by: Roland House and SuperJane Films
    TRT: 86:00
    Filmmaker Linda Duvoisin interviews five inspiring women about how they have overcome obstacles and maintained a passion for life. Julie Brunzell, police officer; Ani DiFranco, musician, poet and entrepreneur; Linda Finney, police supervisor and poet; Myrtle Stedman, artist, writer and architect; and Jimmie Woodruff, retired housekeeper, share their wisdom in frank and provocative discourse on love, work, sex, prejudices, race, gender, violence, and creativity. The five interviews are deftly interwoven to draw connections between the women's very different life experiences.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 86:00 (Box 5)
    - DVD master, TRT 86:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - La Bonne Conduite: 5 Histoires d'Auto Ecole (1999)
    English title: The Way I Look At You: 5 Stories of Driving School
    Directed by: Jean-Stefane Bron
    Produced by: Les Films de la Dernier Heure
    Country: Switzerland
    TRT: 60:00
    Five pairs of driving instructors and students are brought together at one driving school in Lausanne, Switzerland. Diverse in nationality, religion and race, their encounters are both funny and tragic as they attempt to teach and learn, connect and understand.
    .
    - 35mm, reel 1 of 3, 1800 ft. (Reel 101)
    - 35mm, reel 2 of 3, 1800 ft. (Reel 102)
    - 35mm, reel 3 of 3, 1800 ft. (Reel 103)
  - but, the day came (2000)
    Directed by: Eugene Richards
    Produced by: Eugene Richards and Janine Altongy
    Award won: DoubleTake Jury Award for Best Short
    Clarence, a 92-year-old Nebraska farmer, and his family never wanted the day to come when he would have to leave the old farmhouse for a retirement home. But it did. Poetically shot on digital video, capturing a rural Midwestern landscape of decaying farmsteads, this short film documents how a family feels in deciding how their patriarch should spend his last days.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 27:00 (Box 9)
    - DVD master, TRT 27:00 (Box 8)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Festival materials, 2000
    - Program Book, 2000 DoubleTake Film Festival (2000) (Box 6)
    - Programs and Pamphlets, 2000 (Box 13)
    - T-Shirt, 2000 (Box 13)
    - Tote Bag, 2000 (Box 13)
    - Newspaper Insert, 2000 (Box 19)
- DoubleTake Film Festival, 2001
  - Amato: A Love Affair with Opera (2000)
    Directed by: Stephen Ives
    Produced by: Stephen Ives
    TRT: 57:00